Guide to the Reginald Horace Blyth papers, 1948-1970 RL.11762
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Reginald Horace Blyth papers
1948-1970 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Blyth, Reginald Horace
RL.11762
5.75 Linear Feet
Reginald Horace Blyth popularized Japanese poetic forms such as haiku and senryū within English-speaking audiences by publishing insightful, widely read English translations. Born in Essex, England, Blyth studied literature and went to Korea in 1925 to teach at the newly established Imperial University in Keijo (present-day Seoul) and moved to Japan in 1940. During WWII, he was interned in a Japanese camp as a noncombatant alien. After the war, Blyth served as an intermediary between American Occupation leaders and the Japanese. Notably, Blyth helped draft the Ningen Sengen declaration, which stated that Emperor Hirohito was a human being and not divine. Blyth also served throughout the post-war era as a tutor to Crown Prince Akihito. In addition, Blyth was an associate of Zen teacher D.T. Suzuki and other Buddhist practitioners and authors who, along with him, introduced Zen to Western audiences. Blyth's own books include Zen in English Literature and Oriental Classics, the series Zen and Zen Classics, Senryu: Japanese Satirical Verses, and Oriental Humor. The collection includes manuscript drafts, notes, and notebooks for published and unpublished works. Many of the files relate to his books on Japanese poetry, humor, and Zen, as well as to his works about British and American Literature. Other files relate to unpublished works and to research interests about animism, culture and mysticism, the British poet John Clare, language, love, and satanism. The bulk of the Printed Materials series includes an incomplete selection of Blyth's published books as well as newsletters and commentary from the Diamond Sangha in Honolulu.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Correspondence, Writings and Research, and Printed Materials. With few exceptions, Japanese names in this collection guide have been written following Western naming conventions, with the given name first and family name last.
Biographical / Historical
Reginald Horace Blyth popularized Japanese poetic forms such as haiku and senryū within English-speaking audiences by publishing insightful, widely read English translations. Born in Essex, England, Blyth studied literature and went to Korea in 1925 to teach at the newly established Imperial University in Keijo (present-day Seoul) and moved to Japan in 1940. During WWII, he was interned in a Japanese camp as a noncombatant alien. After the war, Blyth served as an intermediary between American Occupation leaders and the Japanese. Notably, Blyth helped draft the Ningen Sengen declaration, which stated that Emperor Hirohito was a human being and not divine. Blyth also served throughout the post-war era as a tutor to Crown Prince Akihito. In addition, Blyth was an associate of Zen teacher D.T. Suzuki and other Buddhist practitioners and authors who along with him introduced Zen to Western audiences. Blyth's own books include Zen in English Literature and Oriental Classics, the series Zen and Zen Classics, Senryu: Japanese Satirical Verses, and Oriental Humor. The bulk of Blyth's work was first published between 1942 and 1963. Blyth died in Tokyo in 1964.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Reginald Horace Blyth papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2019.
Related Materials
Researchers may also be interested in the Norman Waddell papers, 1986-2008, and the Philip Kapleau papers, 1952-2004.
https://library.duke.edu/rubenstein/findingaids/waddellnorman/
https://library.duke.edu/rubenstein/findingaids/kapleauphilip/
Collection Overview
Manuscript drafts, notes, and notebooks for published and unpublished works by Reginald Horace Blyth. Many of the files relate to his books on Japanese poetry, humor, and Zen, as well as his works about British and American Literature. Some materials are written in Japanese. Of note, there are 20 folders of notebooks about senryū poetry, which are written in Japanese and translated into English with explication. Other files relate to unpublished works and research interests about animism, culture and mysticism, the British poet John Clare, language, love, and satanism. The bulk of the Printed Materials series includes an incomplete selection of Blyth's published books as well as newsletters and commentary from the Diamond Sangha in Honolulu.
Zen Buddhism -- Japan -- 20th century.; Haiku.; Senryu.; Japanese poetry.; Diamond Sangha
- Correspondence
  - Inoue, N, undated (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    One letter about Mu, Zen, and poetry
- Writings and Research, 1948-1964 and undated
  Manuscript drafts, notes, and notebooks for published and unpublished works by Blyth. Arranged alphabetically by subject. Many of the files relate to his books on Japanese poetry, humor, and Zen, as well as to his works about British and American Literature. Some materials are written in Japanese. Of note, there are 20 folders of notebooks about senryū poetry, which are written in Japanese and translated into English with explication. It appears that there were a few contributors to the notebooks other than Blyth; these included Toshiko Chiba and Laura Rill. Blyth mentions Toshiko Chiba in the prefaces to several of his books. There are also some haiku translations by Akiko Kobayashi. Other files relate to unpublished works and to research interests about animism, culture and mysticism, the British poet John Clare, language, love, and satanism. Almost none of the files have dates, but they were likely created between 1948 and 1964.
  - Animals notes (Box 1)
  - Animism notes, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Art of Gardening notes (Box 1)
  - Bashō notes (Box 1)
  - Dodoitsu manuscript draft (Box 1)
  - Bible and Shakespeare notes (Box 1)
  - Buddhism notes (Box 17)
  - Christianity and Buddhism typed manuscript draft (Box 1)
  - Culture notes, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Culture and Mysticism notes (Box 1)
  - Culture and Mysticism notes (Box 2)
  - Emerson and Asia (Box 2)
  - Formative Reading Experiences of Children manuscript draft (Box 2)
  - Haiku notes, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Haiku and Bashō notes (Box 17)
  - Haiku chosen and written out by Kobayashi Akiko (Box 2)
  - Toshiko Chiba notebooks of haiku and senryū with English translations (Box 2)
  - Haiku translations (Box 3)
  - History of English literature notebooks (Box 3)
  - Humor notes (Box 3)
  - Ikkū translations (Box 3)
  - Incense Art manuscript draft (Box 3)
  - Inge: Mysticism manuscript draft (Box 3)
  - Japanese riddles, songs, puns, and proverbs (Box 3)
  - John Clare manuscript draft, 4 folders (Box 17)
  - John Clare notes, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Kyōgen notes (Box 17)
  - Kyōgen manuscript draft (Box 4)
  - Kyōka manuscript draft (Box 4)
  - Language notes (Box 4)
  - Love manuscript draft, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Magic notes (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous notes on literature, the tragic-comic, and Zen (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous short quotes and sayings, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Mumonkan notes (Box 5)
  - Music notes (Box 5)
  - Mutamagawa manuscript draft (Box 5)
  - Mysticism (Box 18)
  - Mysticism notebook (Box 5)
  - Mysticism notes (Box 6)
  - Poetry notes, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Poetry and Zen notes (Box 6)
  - Postulations and Expostulations manuscript draft (Box 6)
  - Primitivism notes (Box 6)
  - Religion notes (Box 6)
  - Religion notes, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Religious poetry quotes (Box 7)
  - Satanism, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Senryū and Haiku introduction manuscript draft (Box 8)
  - Senryū Dictionary (Box 8)
  - Senryū, Kyōka (mad poems), 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Senryū in World Literature essay (Box 18)
  - Senryū manuscript draft, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Senryū and Poetry manuscript draft (Box 8)
  - Senryū notebooks (folders 1-5), 5 folders (Box 9)
    Some of the notebooks appear to have several contributors. The names of Laura Rill and Toshiko Chiba are inscribed on the front of many of the notebooks, suggesting that they provided translations to Blyth. The notebooks are in Japanese and English and show edits and notes. There are 20 folders in all, and each folder contains several notebooks.
  - Senryū notebooks (folders 6-11), 6 folders (Box 10)
  - Senryū notebooks (folders 12-18), 7 folders (Box 11)
  - Senryū notebooks (folders 19-20), 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Senryū notes and translations (Box 12)
  - Senryū translations, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Zen senryū manuscript drafts (Box 12)
  - Taoism notes (Box 12)
  - Western literature notes, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Western literature notes (Box 13)
  - Zen (Box 13)
  - Zen and Existentialism notebook (Box 13)
  - Zen and Zen Classics Vol. III, 1960-1962; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Zen and Zen Classics Vol. III, 1960-1962; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Zen and Zen Classics Vol. III, 1960-1962 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Zen and Christianity notes (Box 14)
- Printed Materials, 1948-1970
  Arranged into two subseries: Printed Books by Blyth and Printed Materials by Others.
  - Published Books by Blyth, 1948-1963
    An incomplete selection of Blyth's published books on British and American literature, Buddhism, humor, Korean language, and Japanese poetry. Some books include ownership inscriptions by Norman Waddell and "Akiko." Akiko may refer to Blyth's secretary Akiko Kobayashi, who provided translations to Blyth. Norman Waddell is a scholar of Japanese Zen Buddhism. Some of the books were used for instruction by Blyth and include minimal marginalia. The books are arranged chronologically by the date that each title was first published.
    - Zen in English Literature and Oriental Classics, 1948 (Box 14)
      Presentation copy signed "To Akiko, RH Blyth"
    - Senryu: Japanese Satirical Verses, 1949 (Box 14)
      Signed by Blyth and inscribed "To Akiko"
    - Haiku Vol. 1 Eastern Culture, 1960 (Box 15)
      First printed in 1949, 1960 edition
    - Haiku Vol. 2 Spring, 1960 (Box 15)
      First printed in 1950, 1960 edition
    - A First Book of Korean, 1950 (Box 15)
      By Lee Eun and R.H. Blyth, 2 "specimen copies"
    - A Shortened Version of a Week on the Concord and Merrimack Rivers by Henry David Thoreau, 1951 (Box 15)
      With an introduction by Blyth
    - Buddhist Sermons on Christian Texts, 1952 (Box 15)
      "N.A. Waddell" ownership inscription
    - Haiku Vol. 3 Summer-Autumn, 1957 (Box 15)
      First printed in 1952, 1957 edition
    - Haiku Vol. 4 Autumn-Winter, 1952 (Box 15)
    - Dorothy Wordsworth's Journals, 1953 (Box 15)
    - A Short History of English Literature, 1953 (Box 15)
    - A Survey of English Literature, 1957 (Box 15)
    - Japanese Humour, 1957 (Box 15)
      Inscribed "To Akiko from Ichiban Buraizu"
    - How to Read English Poetry, 1958 (Box 15)
    - Easy Poems, Book Two, 1959 (Box 15)
    - Humour in English Literature, 1959 (Box 15)
    - Oriental Humour, 1963 (Box 15)
      First printed in 1959, 1963 edition
    - Japanese Life and Character in Senryu, 1960 (Box 15)
      "Akiko" inscribed on slipcase
    - Edo Satirical Verse Anthologies, 1961 (Box 15)
  - Printed Materials by Others, 1943-1970
    - Diamond Sangha newsletters, 1963-1970; 2 folders (Box 16)
      Newsletters sent from Robert Aitken's sangha in Hawaii.
    - Diamond Sangha commentary, 1960s; 3 folders (Box 16)
      Commentary on Zen practice by Katsuki Sekida, D.T. Suzuki, and Yasutani Roshi. Edited by Robert Aitken.
    - Monumenta Serica: Journal of Oriental Studies of Catholic University of Peking, 1943 (Box 16)
      Reprint from Vol. VIII about Wumen's "The Gateless Barrier"